[Music]
okay welcome to episode three of our
inventory system series so in this
episode we're going to be covering um
setting up this kind of scene to make it
a bit more like playable i want to have
be able to move around as the character
properly instead of dragging the bean
around like this
and i'm going to put some chests in the
scene so when we start working on the ui
we can have things to go and interact
with and we'll start putting the ui
together as well so let's just jump
straight into it uh where i left off in
the last episode
our players got an inventory uh list
here a list of slots and as we go over
the slots they fill up
and eventually once the inventory is
full stuff won't pick up off the ground
and items can have different stack sizes
so if we set test time one which is the
red spheres to a stack size of five and
we hit play
then we click the player as we go over
we can pick up five of test item one
stack size of item two
is
um
one so we'll pick up them and then we
can start a new stack here of five more
test item ones that stack's full so
we'll start to put um
so the other two went into the next
three slot there so that's where we are
that's where we're at
um the first thing i want to do then is
i just want to make it so we can
actually like you know move around with
wasd
and to do that in this series we're
going to be using the new input system
so i'm going to go up to window package
manager
i'm going to go to unity registry
select input system and then hit install
this is going to install and it will ask
us to restart the editor once and it's
installed you just need to hit yes to
that and it'll restart our project so
i'll catch back up with you after that's
done okay so we're back in unity here
after it's reset um
after the project has restarted so you
can see that the input system is now
in our project
so i'm just going to close this down and
we'll come back to moving the character
in a sec but let's just make a bit of a
scene
to actually move around
um
i'm just going to delete all of these
test items apart from test that the
original test item one and two
just because i want them a bit more
organized um i'm going to right click
create three job 3d object and make a
plane
i'll center this in the world i'm just
going to scale it up
we'll make a new material
this kind of a grayish
color
gray
i'm going to create an empty object i'm
going to call this a
small chest
and again center that in the scene
i'm going to right click um 3d object
make a cube
bring this up
i'm going to make another material
called brown
while up here i'm just gonna make
another one called
gold
so for our
to represent our chest i'm gonna just
duplicate this cube bring it forward
move it up and then let's
scale it down and make this gold
so that's our small chest
and then let's make
uh
oh overdone
and then we'll make big chest
and we'll make that slightly bigger so
we've got small chest and big chest
let's move our small chest
just back over there
big chest
back
rotate we might make more chests later
on well
in fact we will make more chests later
on
so we've got our bean here i'm just
going to add another
i'm going to add a 3d cylinder
oh
and i'm just gonna give him some eyes
just so we can see which direction
they're pointing
now let's add a script called
[Music]
player movement
this i'm just going to get the character
controller.move script if you just
search for unity character controller
script and it's this one
um
let's just steal this
up from the bottom
up to there and then we can
come back to our scripts let's just
paste
paste that in so we've got our character
controller
um here because we're using the new
input system instead of this get access
horizontal axis vertical
for now let's just um
remove these i'll just put zero because
we're using the new input system
i'm just going to get rid of this uh the
jump in stuff because it doesn't seem to
work ever anyway for this character
controller
um
so we can get rid of
jump height whatever
uh let's go back to our
project i'm just gonna drag this player
movement script over into scripts
make a new folder for materials
pop our materials over there to keep
organized
i'm going to create a new folder called
input
and in input i'm going to create a
new input actions called player controls
i'm going to open this up
i'm going to call our action map player
here i'm going to choose passthrough
vector2
under binding
under add binding i'm going to add a 2d
vector composite and i'm just going to
delete this binding that was made
already
so for up i'm going to have the w key
downs the s key left is the a key
right is the d key
i'm gonna save the asset and then i'm
gonna
close this
click generate c sharp assets i'm going
to click the player controls and click
generate c-sharp class and hit apply
over in our player movement script
i'm just going to say play private
player controls called player controls
and in start we can say player controls
is equal to new player controls
and then in our on enable function we
want to say play controls dot enable
and in our
on
disable function we just want to say
player controls dot disable
and then in update
so this
x was the um horizontal axis
so we can say player controls
dot
player dot
new action
okay we don't want it to be called new
action uh we need to go back to our
player control
input action asset and i should have
called this
movement
hit save
x out of this
back to our script
so this is movement
dot read value
vector 2
x
and we could do control c control v and
we'll do
y
for the z axis
okay so if you don't um
understand the input system if you've
not used it before i'll explain these in
just a second um but the first thing
actually is um i've changed the start
method to
awake i'm going to change this to get
component instead of add component
and then i'm going to come up here
and i'm going to say require component
type of
character controller and i've also put
the kind of null operator here so player
controls question mark dot enable so if
player controls isn't null then we'll
enable them and if the if it's not null
and we disable we'll disable them as
well so back in our project let's add
the player movement script to our
character controller and you'll see that
it's in the ground there the capsule
collider
and
we just need to raise this up by one
so our character controller is now on
the ground
so the way the input action asset is
working so we called it player controls
that's the input action asset
which is also the name of the script
that was generated when we clicked
generate c-sharp class
inside there we have an action map
called player we create an action called
movement
and under that we put a 2d vector
which is controlled by um up and down
uns and then left and right is a and d
and if you think of this as like a
2d kind of uh sort of
a unit circles we've got our circle
again i'm on my mouse here
so it's not going to be perfect
this is our y-axis this is our x-axis
we've got a and d
control our x-axis
w and s control our y-axis so if i'm
holding w down we're going to be up here
so that's going to be
um 1.
if i'm holding s down this will be minus
1 a it'll be minus 1 on the x and then x
d sorry it'll be plus one on the x
so in our script when we're reading the
value we've got player controls which
again was the name of the input action
this is the actual action map player
movement was the action that we made and
then we're reading the vector2 value of
that
and we've taken the x value for the x of
our movement vector and we're taking the
y value for the z of our
vector3 so the y is going to be forward
so that was w and s and then the x is a
and d for left and right
so all things
working as they should be um let's just
move our camera into a better position
so just so we can see our objects and um
chest
as we start moving we can walk around
and pick up the items uh
we're going very slowly
so i'm just going to go back to our
player movement script and i'm going to
um
i'll just make this public because
we could serialize the field but i'm
just going to make it public
so we'll go back to our player
player speed let's set that to five
let's see if that's better
there we go we're moving around a lot
better now so we can we can move around
we've got our chests which we can bump
into we can't interact with them yet but
we will work on that
okay so we've got our bean um
i don't like the colors i've chosen
there we go i've got a blue bean we've
got our test items we've got a chest
which we'll interact with later
okay so now we need to start working on
our actual um
ui so let's right click create a
ui
canvas
and we'll just call this uh we'll just
leave that called canvas because we're
using the new input system on our event
system we just need to click this here
replace the input system with the new
input system module
we do that that's all working fine
so
we go to our canvas and we want to say
screen space and overlay that's fine
but we want to come down to ui scale
mode and change to scale with screen
size
i'm just going to put in
1920 by 1080 as and the first thing i'm
going to do under this is i'm going to
come to our canvas i'm going to right
click create empty and i'm just going to
call this mouse object
and our mouse object is going to have
an image
and it's also going to have
some text i'm going to use text text
mesh pro we just need to import tmp
essentials so i'll just hit that
we'll close this window and i'm going to
hit the 2d button up here
select our mouse object and then press f
just so we fly over to that
and then i'm going to
just position this so i'm just going to
type in
10 just so i can get kind of what it
looks like
let's center it
i'm going to make it black
i'm just going to put this in the corner
here of our image
so actually we don't want to center it
um
on the alignment we want to right align
it
and bring this up here and let's resize
this box
because obviously if we had a hundred
items we want it to come out from that
right hand side we don't want it to be
centered so we'll do let's put 99 as a
default
i'm going to bring it away from that
corner and check auto size that'll fill
the box
nicely
i might actually reduce the
[Music]
max the maximum size a little bit
and i'll just place that there so this
is our mouse object
for mouse object uh we're going to add a
script i'm going to come over to uh
inventory scripts i'm going to right
click create
c sharp script and we're going to say
inventory
uh
i'm just going to call this my mouse
item
data
we'll open this up
and for now let's just get a reference
to the image um so we need to be using
unity engine dot ui
and we need to use tm pro
and let's get a public image reference
to our item sprite and we'll get a
public tm
pro
ugui
text mesh pro you
you gooey
um
and we'll say item
count
so go to our mouse object and let's just
add the
mouse item data script and we'll just
drag in image and drag in text for now
and then um on void awake
i'm just going to set the item sprite
dot color equal to color dot
clear to make it invisible and i'm going
to say item count dot text
equal to
just a null string
so when we hit play that'll disappear
that's great we don't we don't need to
see that if we're not currently actively
holding an item so that's our mouse
object
which we'll come back to later
um
now let's create a panel so create
ui
panel and we're going to start making
the hot bar so i'm just going to call
this hot
player
hot bar
and let's
check the whole thing
i'm going to click um
here the anchor presets button i'm going
to hold down alt
and see that we changed the pivot in the
snap in so i'm going to hold down alt
i'm going to change the um anchor pivot
to the bottom center
see that that moved there
so now as we start to like scale you'll
see now that that kind of snaps to the
bottom so if i
start to resize this it's kind of
anchored at the bottom of the screen
so let's just drag that down there for
our panel here um i'm just going to add
a content
size fitter
and we can set that to preferred size
for both of those
and i'm going to have a horizontal
layout group
in that i'm going to give some padding
of 15 with a spacing of 10.
child alignment i'll leave at um upper
left and child force expands that's fine
so now i'm going to make a inventory
slot to go on our hot bar and this is
going to be kind of
it's going to match the slots on the
back end like we're going to pair it
with a slot on the back end
so to our hotbar
i'm just going to right click create
empty
and i'm just going to call this
inventory
slot underscore ui
and then underneath this
game object i'm going to right click and
i'm going to
go to ui and choose image
it's just going to be like just like the
mouse slot so we're going to have an
image
i'm going to have um ui
text for text mesh pro
and in fact
let's just copy let's make a duplicate
i'm going to rename this to item count
ctrl d to duplicate it and i'm just
going to drag it under our inventory
slot ui
and then
reset the position on the x and y
rename it to remove the one there
let's just zoom in and position it where
we want it we want it down at the bottom
of our inventory slot
and to the actual top level parent of
inventory slot i'm just going to add a
component i'm going to add a button
component and this is how we're going to
interact with the screen so it's not
going to be a drag and drop kind of
style interface it's going to be a
you click on the slot to pick it up and
then you click on another slot to place
it down
the reason for that is because i want
this to be able to work on game
controllers and you can't drag and drop
on a game controller unless you were
manipulating the mouse with a joystick
and i don't really like that this could
be more minecraft style or stardew
valley style you can highlight a slot
click it
go to a different slot place it so we're
going to put a button
on our inventory slot ui
for the target graphic we need to add an
image so i'm just going to choose image
and drag our image
under the graphic of the button that's
fine for now we can put a
source image in there
in a
second but i'm now going to um
come back over to our assets right click
create folder prefabs
and under our prefab folder i'm going to
drag our inventory slot ui i'm going to
make a prefab out of it and then i'm
just going to duplicate this um nine
times so we've got 10 slots on our
hotbar so
ctrl d
until we've got uh 10 10 inventory slots
and you can see our hot bar here
i'm just gonna
remove
gizmos out of this scene so you can see
that we've got our inventory slots
here on our hotbar
and then we've got a placeholder for our
mouse slot
so on our inventory slot ui
prefab
we're going to add a script to it so i'm
going to go back to our scripts folder
and i'm going to make a
folder called ui scripts
i'm just going to go in here right click
create c sharp script i'm going to call
this inventory slot
underscore ui
and i'll open that up in visual studio
so this is obviously a mono behavior
we don't need these two using statements
but we will need um
using unity engine dot
ui
we'll need to use text mesh pro again so
using tm pro and we can get rid of start
and update for now um and instead we're
going to do is we're going to serialize
field
private
image sprite
item
sprite can do a serialized field for the
private text mesh pro u-gui
which is our item count
serialize field
um private inventory
slot
our assigned
inventory slot
which is our back end slot that's
represented by the actual ui element so
we can make a private button
called button i'm going to make a public
property
so a public inventory slot and assigned
inventory slot with a getter for our
private variable then over in our void
awake function
i'm gonna say item sprite dot sprite is
equal to null
item sprite dot color is equal to color
dot clear
item count dot text is equal to a blank
string we're going to get our button
component so button.getcomponent
button
and then if button isn't null we're
gonna subscribe to it's on click event
so we're gonna add a listener
and we're gonna
add a method called on ui slot click
which we can make
here public void on u i
slot click
so in here
we're going to
in a second make a display another class
which we're going to access and we're
going to access that class so access
display class
um
function so the relevant function on
that display class which we'll make and
i'm going to make a public
void clear slot function
which is actually just going to do
this
but i'm also going to check the assigned
inventory slot
is
if it's null
then we're going to clear
the slot there as well except we're
clearing this slot on the um
ui we want to make sure that that's
reflected in the system as well
so we'll just do clear slot here and
then we can actually just get rid of
this i can call clear slot in the awake
function as well then i'm going to make
a public void
init function for like initialized
and i'm just going to pass in a slot
when we initialize this slot so
inventory slot slot
i'm going to say
assigned inventory slot equals inventory
slot
or
slot i've just called it not in slot
so assigned inventory slot is equal to
the slot that we've passed in
and then i'm going to update the ui
slot so this is going to be the graphics
so it's going to pass in
it's going to pass the slot on
so public
void update ui slot which takes in an
inventory slot called slot
in here we can see um
if
inventory slot dot data
if slot
dot data item data is uh
not equal to null
then we will set our item sprite
dot sprite equal to the
uh slot dot item data dot
icon
and we'll make the sprite visible by
setting the color back to color.white
if the data is null then we just want to
clear this slot
so if for some reason we've passed in a
slot that has no data in it we just want
to clear that slot anyway um just to
make sure that that's reflected properly
so that's the the icon and then we also
want to check the stack size so if slot
dot stack size
is greater than one
we'll say item count dot text is equal
to
slot dot stack size dot two string
so if we've only got one of the item we
won't display the number
uh that that's down to you um
maybe you want it to display it when
there is only one but i prefer it so if
there's only one item we just don't have
a number next to it
so we can say else
item count
dot text is equal to
a null string so
so we can actually put this
inside here
and i want a version of this method that
we can call without passing in a slot so
we can just
refresh it um
directly
so i'm just going to say update ui slot
which won't take in any kind of
arguments and i can just say that if our
assigned inventory slot isn't null
then we'll update the ui slot by passing
in our assigned inventory slot
so the reason for this is we may want to
reflect we may just want to refresh this
slot without passing in an inventory
slot so this is a good way to do that
we'll just refresh it based on the
assigned inventory slot that we've given
it anyway when we set up the slots okay
so let's just pop back over to the
editor and set this up so if we go over
to our prefab let's add our um
inventory slot ui script to our prefab
then we can say um
item sprite is that i am count is that
our assigned inventory slot
um it starts as null that's fine
so let's go back and then we can see
that our slot uis here
they've all been updated to have a
reference to their own um images and
item counts so that's grand
so now we need our inventory display
class so
again let's go back to our scripts
folder ui scripts and let's go over to
so let's right click create
create c sharp script and we're going to
call this inventory display
and we'll double click and open that
so this is going to be an abstract class
we're not going to use this class
directly
and we're going to want to get rid of
start and update
and we don't need system.collections we
will be using
generic though and we want unizing unity
engine dot events
and also using unity engine dot input
system okay so this is gonna need a few
different um variables so we're gonna
need a protected
inventory system so this is going to be
the inventory system
that we want to display
so inventory system
inventory
system
and again we'll make a getter for this
so public inventory system inventory
system
we get
inventory system
i want a protected
i'm going to keep all my getters down at
the bottom
um so we want a protected
dictionary and this is going to take in
um an inventory slot ui
and inventory
slots
we'll just call this the slot dictionary
do you see now that we we basically
marry up a ui
slot
against its like actual slot in the
inventory system so we go back to our
little graphic here
you can see that we've got the system
and we've got the ui these ui slots at
the
physical kind of in-game representations
of these system slots so you can see
that this is how
it's going to look it's going to when
it's got an item it's going to display
the items graphic when it's got
an item and there's a stack size greater
than one it'll display a number
of that
to represent the stack size so this is
the representation of the actual slots
in the the data sort of system the back
end of it
so by using a dictionary if we pass in a
ui slot we can get out the slot that
it's sort of married to
which is great that's exactly what we
need to be doing and i'm going to make
this publicly accessible as well so
public dictionary inventory slot ui is
the key inventory slot
as the value
and i'll say slot dictionary and we'll
get the slot dictionary
and i'm gonna also serialize field
mouse
item data
i'll call this mouse
inventory
item and we can set this in the
inspector
another option would be to use um to
make a singleton out of this we can get
it that way
um that's the way i did it in my test
project but
to not have to go through what a
singleton is and all that uh
we're just gonna call this we're just
gonna set this in the inspector and make
sure that we do so we're gonna need a
public
abstract
void function that our derived classes
are going to
use
so that's going to be
public abstract void assign slots
and this is going to take in
the inventory system which is the
inv
to display
so when we assign the slots um
we're going to create this dictionary so
we need to know which slots to marry up
with the actual inventory slot ui kind
of representations
um i'm gonna make a protected void
uh protected virtual void sorry
called update
slots
update slot
and then this is going to take in an
inventory slot
called
updated slot
and this isn't abstract because it's
going to be the same
it's going to be the same no matter
which um kind of variation of this class
we make so we can just define it here
so we could say for each
slot so variable slot in the slot
dictionary
if
if slot dot value is equal to the
updated slot
that we've passed in
then let's
update the ui slot of the
corresponding inventory slot so now this
is getting quite confusing because i've
you know stuff's kind of called the same
thing so
on our inventory display class we've got
this function update slot we're going to
pass in
a system
slot
this is this this script where it's got
all of the actual like system elements
to it i'm going to pass that slot in and
then we're going to check for every slot
in our slot dictionary we're going to
loop through them
and if that slot that we're looking at
if the value of that entry is the slot
that was passed in
then we're going to update the ui slot
that corresponds to the inventory system
slot
and here that's the key because you'll
see that you know the inventory slot ui
is our key the inventory slot system
isn't
the key it's the value so we can update
the ui slot there
so this is the slot value
the
under the hood
inventory slot
this is the slot key
the ui representation
of the value
this will have um
another function called um slot clicked
which we're not going to do in this
episode because it's quite a long script
that's probably going to be an episode
all on its own
but this is going to take in a clicked
slot
for now we'll just say
debug dot
log
slot clicked
so this function is what we're going to
use on our actual inventory slot so if i
go back to inventory slot i'm going to
make a
public property of inventory
display
and we don't need to set this in the
inspector so i don't need a private
version of this i can just say get
private
set
i need to call it something so parent
display
and here in the awake function we can
just set parent
display equal to transform dot parent
dot get component
inventory display so in our on ui slot
click function this is where we can say
parent display
dot
on slot
so that's where we say parent display
slot clicked this which will go through
to the inventory display function and
it'll debug dot log slot clicked so the
last thing i want to do is i just want
to make the first kind of derived script
from this the first kind of instance of
the script so
um
in our ui scripts folder i'm going to
create c-sharp script i'm going to call
this static inventory
display
we'll open this up so the first thing
this is going to do is going to
implement
it's going to inherit from inventory
display and you see that we've got a
squiggle here if we press alt and enter
we can implement the abstract class
which is this assign slots function
we'll get rid of um
start and update from here
what we actually need to do is an
inventory display
i want to make a
public
virtual
void start
just in case we need to do stuff in
there later
and then in our static inventory display
i can do um public
override void start
and this doesn't need to be public
actually
sorry that needs to be protected
so protected override void start we can
call our base start
so at the top of our static inventory
display i'm gonna need two
fields so i want a serialized field
private inventory holder
called
inventory holder
and serialize field
private
inventory slot ui
array
called slots
now
now in our start function i can say if
inventory holder is not equal to null
so if we've actually assigned it in the
inspector
let me say the inventory system is equal
to the inventory holder
dot
inventory system
we can subscribe to the inventory
systems on inventory changed function
and we're going to subscribe our update
slots function to that event now the
update slot function to the event so
that's the method that we've can we've
got on our inventory display here that
event is this this on slot changed so
when we do something and add something
to the inventory
we call on inventory slot changed um and
we invoke that
here i'm just gonna else and i'll do
debug.log warning
no inventory assigned to
this.gameobject just so we know if
something's gone wrong
and then after all of that we can say
assign slots
inventory system so we can assign our
slots and pass in
our inventory holders inventory system
again inventory system is over on our
inventory display class it's this
protected inventory system um
variable here and what we're going to do
here is we're going to
get rid of this throw new exception and
we're going to say slot dictionary
is equal to a new dictionary of
inventory slot uis and inventory slots
and then we're going to say for int i
whilst i is less than the inventory
system dot inventory size
which because this is a static display
we've set this up in the inspector to
have 10 slots
so we need to make sure that the
inventory system that we're pairing it
with also has 10 slots
we could check for that and debug it and
i know you know i'm looking for the
hotbar which is i've said in for my game
has 10 slots so i've represented that
over on the ui
once that's set up that should not
change you could obviously you would
implement a check if you wanted to so
you could check your array size
versus the inventory size and if it's
not the same then do an error
i mean i suppose for good practice let's
just do that quickly so if slots
dot length is not equal
to
um
inventory system dot inventory size
then again debug.log
inventory slots out of sync on
this dark game object
so for int i equals zero whilst it's
less than the inventory size
we're going to add to our slot um
our slot dictionary
dot add i'm going to pass in the key
which is the
slots
i
so it'll be 0 1 2 3 so it's the
corresponding slot in our array so slots
i
and then the value is going to be the
inventory system
dot inventory
i and i can't seem to get inventory so
i've obviously not made a
getter for it so let's just go to
inventory holder inventory system
oh i called inventory slots here that's
why so
um inventory
slots
i
so that's our value
this is our key so this is the ui slot
and this is the value
of the actual like system slot so
we've added that to our dictionary and
then we just want to initialize
the ui slot so we say inventory slot
so we can say inventory system dot
inventory
slots
i
because remember the
[Music]
init function takes in
an inventory slot an assigned inventory
slot and then it updates the slot as
well
so let's just go back into unity i'm
going to click on player hotbar
i'm going to add our static inventory
script or static inventory display
for the inventory holder i'm just going
to drag in our player
and for slots i'm going to open up our
hot bar
i'm going to click the lock up here to
lock the inspector and i'm going to
get all of our inventory slots and i'm
going to drag them into our slots array
now i want them to be they need to be in
the correct order so
you know slot 0 which is this one is
element 0 slot 9 or slot 10 sorry
is this one
so this is the size 10.
and while we're here i'm just going to
drag
the mouse object into the mouse
inventory item
i just had an error i've put
button.getcomponent
button i need to say button equals get
component button
so now we need to get some assets so i'm
going to go create
folder and i'm going to call this
graphics
okay so that's um
so on our inventory slot prefab i'm
going to change um
we have this image here
i'm just going to make this like a brown
kind of color
to kind of indicate the the slot being
empty and then we have an image here
which if i disable that we can see the
slots now brown this image that was
currently white should go clear when we
hit play
because that's the actual item sprite um
so let's even you know reduce the
width and height of this so
85.85 so this is the actual slot which
is brown
and then there's the um
item image which is white in this case
and let's go back to our inventory slot
go to overrides hit apply all so here's
our slots with an item sprite in it and
when we hit play
we're going to clear them out and we've
got our slots now so when we hit play
they go clear because they've been
assigned a blank inventory slot we can
walk around when we pick up an item
so we've got our test item here uh
there's currently no sprite icon
attached to it but it will go white so
when we go over an item it'll go white
and we'll see that we've got an item in
that slot
go over another item that slot now has
an item in it if we've got um multiples
of this item so
test item 2 can be stacked so let's just
make a couple of these
hit play
when we go over you can see that we've
now got three of these test items uh in
the slot
but there's no icon so in the next
episode we're going to build upon this
system we'll add in some icons for these
and then we're going to work on the
actual click functionality so at the
minute when i click the um slots nothing
happens like you can see that i haven't
picked it up i've not done anything so
that's what we're going to work on next
as always if you're watching these kind
of as they're coming out and the full
series is already out and over on my
patreon which is patreon.com
when you support on patreon you'll also
get access to the project file packages
for um each episode as well so even if
you're watching and they're all out it's
worth heading over there anyway if you
want to compare your code to mine you
can do that by downloading the project
files if this episode didn't make sense
if there was something that was unclear
please do let me know in the comments
below or join the discord server which
is linked in the description
uh me or someone else may be able to
help you if you're having trouble there
for now thanks for watching and i'll see
you in the next one bye
you